The Life of Muhammadﷺ, The Madinan Period, Volume 1
By Imam Anwar Al_Awlaki,
اَعُوْذُ بِاللهِ مِنَّ الشِّيْطَانِ الرَّجِيْمِ۝
بِسْمِ اللهِ الرَّحْمَانِ الرَّحِيْمَ۝
اَلْحَمْدُ لله ، وَالصَّلَاةُ وَالسَّلَامُ عَلى سَيِّدِنَا محمد وَعَلَى اَلِهِ وَصَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ
Hassan Bin Thabit رضي الله عنه, as we mentioned previously
was, what we could call him the head of the media effort of Rasool Allah ﷺ,
he was the one who would respond back with poetry against the poets of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) and the other enemies of Islam.
So, Hassan Bin Thabit رضي الله عنه said a lot of lines of poetry,
talking about the treachery and the betrayal of those tribes in Najd(نجد),
who killed the 70 Qurr'ah(قرا), the teachers of Qur'an.
Obviously, translating lines of poetry into different language, you lose the beauty of it
but he has some wonderful lines of poetry talking about those events.
Az-Zubair Bin Awwam رضي الله عنه and I also think I mentioned this before,
he would name his children after the Shuhadaa(شهداء).
So he named two of his sons, after two of the Shuhadaa(شهداء) in Bier Maoona(بئر ماعونه).
One of them was Urwa(عروة) and the other one was Al-Mundhir(المنذر).
So, two of the sons of Az-Zubair(الزبير) were named after Shuhadaa(شهداء).
It says that Zubair(زبير) and Talha(طلحه) were friends,
and both of them belong to the group of 10
who were given the glad tidings of Jannah(جنة).
Talha(طلحه), he would name his sons, after the Ambiyaa(أنبياء),
and Zubair(زبير) would name them, after the Shuhadaa(شهداء).
Rasool Allah ﷺ also during that period of time got married to Zainab Bint Khuzaimah(زينب بنت خزيمه)
and she is called Umm-Ul-Masakeen(ام المساكين) the mother of the poor.
Why.? Because he used to take care of the poor and give them food, give them money, she was very caring of the poor.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ married her.
She was the wife of Abdullah Bin Jahash(عبدالله بن جحش), who was killed in the Battle of Uhud(أحَد).
And we can see here in the marriages of Rasool Allah ﷺ an element of social welfare
Rasool Allah ﷺ taking care of his followers.
So, after Abdullah Bin Jahash(عبدالله بن جحش) died as a Shaheed(شهيد).
Rasool Allah ﷺ marries his wife and takes care of her.
And we can see that throughout the marriages of Rasool Allah ﷺ
and also in many of the marriages of the Sahabah(صحابه),
they didn't want to leave any woman behind without a husband, without a family.
And that was part of the reason or the Hikmah(حكمة) behind polygamy.
One should not think that it's solely for the purpose of satisfying one desires,
there are some other aspects to marriage, bring up a Muslim family, taking care of one another.
وَجَعَلَ بَيْنَكُمْ مَوَدَّةً وَرَحْمَةً ۚ
As Allahعَزّوجَلّ says.
Rasool Allah ﷺ also got married to Ummo Salamah(ام سلمه).
Ummo Salamah رضي الله عنها is from Quraish(قريش), she's from Bannu Makhzoom(بنو مخزوم), an important family in Quraish(قريش),
this is the family of Khalid Bin Waleed(خالد بن وليد), by the way.
And her husband, Abu Salamah(ابوسلمه) was one of the early Sahabah(صحابه),
he made Hijrah(هجرة) to Al-Habasha(حبشه) and he also made Hijrah(هجرة) to Madina,
so he's one of those who made the two Hijrah(هجرة)'s
and he fought in the Battle of Uhud(أحَد) and he was injured.
Now his injury was starting to heal,
Rasool Allah ﷺ sends him on another mission,
and during that mission, his injury starts all over again, and he ends up dying.
Now, before that Abu Salamah(ابوسلمه) has a conversation with his wife.
He tells her, if a husband dies
and his wife does not get married after him,
they would be brought together again in Jannah(جنة).
If both of them are destined to go to Jannah(جنة).
So, Abu Salamah(ابوسلمه) told his wife, How about, we make an agreement,
If I die, you do not get married, if you die I don't get married.
She said: Fine, I agree.
He then told her: No.
I asked Allahعَزّوجَلّ,
If I die then He replaces me with somebody better,
who will marry you and will not harm you or hurt you.
Ummo Salamah(أم سلمه) would then say and who is better than Abu Salamah(ابوسلمه).
Who will I find in the world, better than Abu Salamah(ابوسلمه).
So this shows you that they had a very good relationship.
When he died she went to Rasool Allah ﷺ and told him Abu Salamah(ابوسلمه) is dead.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: Say, O Allah forgive me and forgive him
and replace me with somebody better.
وَاعقُبْنِيْ مِنْهُ عُقْبَهْ حَسَنَهْ
Or give me something that is better.
And she made that Dua(دُعَا),
Abu Bakr Siddique رضي الله عنه proposed marriage, she refused,
Umar Bin Khattab(عمر بن خطاب) proposes marriage, she refuses.
And then Rasool Allah ﷺ
اَرْسَلَ إلَيْهَا يَخْطبُهَا
He proposed marriage, she said: Marhaba(مرحبا), Welcome.
But tell Rasool Allah ﷺ
اِنِّيْ غَيْرَة وَ اِنِّيْ مَسْبِيَّه وَلَيْسَ اَحَدٌ مِنْ اَوْلِيَآئي شَهَدْ
Tell Rasool Allah ﷺ that I am a jealous woman,
and I have kids, young kids, and none of my Walii(ولي) are present.
So I agree, but let Rasool Allah ﷺ know my condition
I'm a very jealous woman and Rasool Allah ﷺ is already married.
And I have kids and these kids are gonna be a burden on him
and then none of my Wallii(ولي) are here to marry me to you.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
اَمَّا قَوْلُكِ اِنِيْ مُسْبِيَة فَاِنَّ الله سَيَكفيْكِ صبْيَانَكْ
You said that you have children, Allahعَزّوجَلّ will take care of those kids.
وَاَمَّا قَوْلُكِ اِنَّيْ غَيْرَة فَسَأدعُو الله اَنْ يَذْهَبَ غَيْرَتُكِ
You said that you are jealous I'm gonna ask Allahعَزّوجَلّ to take that jealousy away.
وَاَمَّا الْاَوْلِيَآءْ  فَلَيْسَ اَحَدُ مِّنْهُمْ اِلَّا سَيَرْضَى بِي
And the Wallii(ولي)'s who are absent,
none of them will refuse to marry you to me, all of them will be happy that you would marry me.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ marries Ummo Salamah(ام سلمه).
In another narration it said that she told him,
I mean, I agree, but I'm an old woman, I'm getting old.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
If you are old I'm older than you.
And I think this also shows you, the intention of Rasool Allah ﷺ, in his marriage from Ummo Salamah رضي الله عنها.
And I talked about this, in my series on the life of Rasool Allah ﷺ in Makkah.
We talked about his marriages and the objectives that his marriages would serve.
So, the marriages of Rasool Allah ﷺ were marriages for the sake of the Ummah(امة), for the sake of the religion.
Ummo Salamah رضي الله عنها, narrated 338 Ahadith(احاديث),
very important to Ahadith(احاديث), some in Bukhari(بخاريْ), some in Muslim(مسلم).
And she conveyed to us this knowledge from Rasool Allah ﷺ.
So, that is one of the reasons, why Allahعَزّوجَلّ destined Rasool Allah ﷺ to marry Ummo Salamahرضي الله عنها
because everything happened, according to the destiny of Allahعَزّوجَلّ and His plan for this religion.
So, his marriage to Ayesha(عائشه) was a Barakah(بركة) for us.
His marriage with Zainab(زينب) was a Barakah(بركة) for us.
His marriage to Khadijah(خديجه) was a Barakah(بركة) for us.
His marriage to Ummo Salamah(ام سلمه) was a Barakah(بركة) for us.
All of his marriages served a purpose in Islam, for us.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ married her and
he said that I'm going to give you a furniture equal to that which I gave to Zainab(زينب).
So, what was this furniture?
Did they go to what are those famous, furniture places IKEA, whatever
and buy new set, furniture, 10's of thousands of dollars worth of furniture for the newly wed couple.
What was the furniture that Rasool Allah ﷺ got for Ummo Salamah(ام سلمه)?
Keep in mind here we're talking about the best of mankind.
The one, who, if he wanted he could have spent on his wives, all the money that he could.
Rasool Allah ﷺ was getting money from all of these Ghazawaat(غزوات) Ghameena(غنيمه) that was coming in,
Rasool Allah ﷺ could have spent that lavishly on his wives and nobody would have complained.
I mean he's the Messenger of Allah, he deserves to have his family live the best life,
who would have dare to complain about that.
But Rasool Allah ﷺ was setting an example for his Ummah(امة) in Zuhud(زهد), austerity.
He said;
اَمَا اِنِّيْ لَا اَنْقُصكِ مِمَّا اَعْطَيْتُ فُلَانَ
يَحْيَيْنْ وَ جَرَّتَيْنْ وِسادَةٌ مِنْ أَدَمٍ حَشْوُها لِيفٌ
I will give you a no less than what I gave so and so.
I gave her two stone Mills, two clay jars
and a pillow stuffed with leaf, leaf is palm leaves.
That was the furniture two stone Mills, two clay jars and a pillow, that was it.
That was the furniture that Rasool Allah ﷺ bought for Ummo Salamah رضي الله عنها, very simple life.
And he spent three days with her, when he got married to her.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ says;
لِلْبِكْرِ سَبْعْ وَللثَيِّبْ ثَلَاثْ
For a person who was married to more than one women.
As soon as he gets married to the second wife or the third or the fourth.
If she is a virgin, then he spends seven days with her.
If she is widowed or divorced then he spends three days with her,
so since Ummo Salamah(ام سلمه) is a widow Rasool Allah ﷺ spent three days with her.
Also during that year, Al-Hassan Bin Ali Bin Abi Talib(الحسن بن علي بن ابي طالب) was born.
When he was born, Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) brought to Rasool Allah ﷺ, the good news
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: What did he name him?
He said, we named him Harb(حرب),
Harb(حرب) means war.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: No, he is Hassan(حسن).
Rasool Allah ﷺ did not like these harsh names, Harb(حرب) and Stone and
you have sakher(صخر) you have Harb(حرب), you've all of these tough names.
Rasool Allah ﷺ did not like that
and he changed the name from Harb(حرب) to Hassan(حسن).
Hassan(حسن) means nice beautiful, kind.
It has all of these pleasant meanings.
This is the name that he chose for his grandson Al-Hassan Bin Ali رضي الله عنه.
Also we see here that it is he, who named his grandson, Al-Hassan رضي الله عنه.
He made Azaan(آذان) in his ear, according to the Hadith(حديث),
he asked his mother Fatima(فاطمه) to shave his head
and then weigh it and pay the equivalent weight in silver as Sadaqah(صدقه) Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله)
and also he made Aqeeqah(عقيقه) for him,
they slaughtered for him two sheep, that was Aqeeqah(عقيقه) of Al-Hassan رضي الله عنه.
We're talking here about various events that happened during the fourth year of Hijrah(هجرى), after the Battle of Uhud(أحَد).
Also during that time Rasool Allah ﷺ calls in, Zaid Bin Thabit رضي الله عنه and he tells him
يَا زَيْدْ تَعَلَّمَ كِتَابَة يَهُوْدْ فَاِنِيْ واللَّهِ ما آمَنُ يَهودَ علَى كتابي
O Zaid(زيد), Learn the Hebrew language because I cannot trust, the Jews.
I don't trust them to read my letters for me, I don't trust them
hiring any one of them to be my assistant to read the letters that I received from them or to write back to them.
Since Rasool Allah ﷺ was illiterate, he had to have these assistance
to write letters for him and to read the letters that he received.
So, there was some correspondence between Rasool Allah ﷺ and the Jews.
So, he wanted a Muslim to be responsible for writing those letters and reading them for him.
Zaid رضي الله عنه said that I learned the Hebrew language in 15 days.
Subhaan Allah(سبحان الله) learning a new foreign language in 15 days
that shows you the persistence and the hard work of the Sahabah رضي الله عنه,
within 15 days, he was ready to go, he learned a foreign language.
So probably for all of those brothers and sisters want to learn Arabic
you could learn a lot from the example of Zaid Bin Thabit رضي الله عنه,
Zaid Bin Thabit(زيد بن ثابت) I mean, shouldn't take you years that you just plan to take the first step,
It just took Zaid(زيد) fifteen(15) days to learn it the whole thing.
Now, learning Arabic is important very important.
And I would urge my brothers and sisters to take it seriously.
Without the Arabic language there is going to remain a barrier between you and understanding the religion of Allahعَزّوجَلّ,
since the original text of this religion is in Arabic language,
whether we're talking about Qur'an or Ahadith(احاديث) of Rasool Allah ﷺ,
so it's very important that you put in the effort into learning Arabic.
And if you make the Niyyah(نية) and you're sincere
Allah will make a way out for you, Allah will make it easy for you, you will be able to learn it.
But just put in the effort,
make the intention put in the effort be willing to sacrifice time and money for it
and In Sha Allah(اِنْ شَاءالله عَزّوجَلّ)  Allah will help you.
If Zaid(زيد) learned a foreign language that is not necessary as a Muslim.
What about learning a language that is necessary and that's the Arabic language.
I also want to say here that Muslims are going to need experts in foreign languages, linguists.
The Muslims will need people, who will be able to study the literature of other nations
the political situation of other nations, the economical situation of other nations.
And that's why it's important for Muslims to learn foreign languages and to have Muslim experts
in each and every language of the world or important language of the world.
Rasool Allah ﷺ, here had Zaid(زيد) learned the Hebrew language
because that was the language in which he had correspondence with Al-Yahood(اليهود),
now a days Muslims have correspondence with many nations of the world,
so it's important that Muslims learn these foreign languages.
The next important event occurred in the fourth year of Hijrah(هجرة).
We talked about Umayyah Bin Amr Adh-Dhamri(امية بن عمرو الضمري).
Actually I think I didn't mention this.
Umayyah Adh-Dhamri(امية  الضمري), he saw two men sleeping under a tree.
He asked them, who do you belong to?
So they said: We belong to so and so tribe.
And this was the tribe that killed the 70 men, the Qur'rraa(قرآء).
So, he went aside until they fell asleep and he killed them.
He thought that he has done something right, by killing these two men
because they belong to the treacherous tribe.
But it turned out that these two men had an agreement with Rasool Allah ﷺ,
these two men specifically had the peace agreement with Rasool Allah ﷺ.
So, Rasool Allah said to Umayyah Bin Amr Adh-Dhamri(امية بن عمرو الضمري)
you have killed two men, I'm gonna have to pay their blood money.
So these men were killed, mistakenly, they shouldn't have been killed.
Therefore Rasool Allah ﷺ is going to have to pay their blood money
now you see here the ruling that
لَيَقْتِلْ مُسلِمْ بِكَافِرْ
A Muslim is not killed for the sake of a disbeliever that's an important rule of fiqh(فقه).
So, even though Umayyah(امية) here have killed two men that shouldn't have been killed,
he is not executed, but the Muslims pay their blood money.
So, this is an important rule of fiqh(فقه).
Now, remember that Rasool Allah ﷺ had an agreement with the Jewish tribes
that they would support each other in blood money
that was mentioned in the Waseeqah(وثيقه), that we read.
They would support each other in blood money.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ goes with Abu Bakr(ابو بكر), Umar(عمر) some of other Sahabah(صحابه),
they go to Bannu Nadhir(بنونضير), this Jewish tribe called Bannu Nadhir(بنونضير), they go to them
and Rasool Allah ﷺ tells them,
These two men have been killed, so I want you to support me in paying their blood money.
They said: We agree and we will help you, O Muhammad(محمد).
Rasool Allah ﷺ is sitting under this wall of theirs
and they pretend that they're going to bring money to help Rasool Allah ﷺ,
while they went to conspire and plan on how to assassinate him,
they said; you're never going to find him in a better position, to assassinate than this,
he is right under your wall have somebody climb up and throw a stone on him and let's get rid of him.
once and for all, let's get rid of this problem.
So, they conspired to assassinate the messenger of Allahعَزّوجَلّ,
something this is not new, they have tried to do that with Eesa عليه السّلام,
they've tried to do that to plenty of other messengers of Allah,
sometimes they succeeded sometimes they fail.
Rasool Allah ﷺ receives revelation from Allahعَزّوجَلّ
Jibreel(جِبْرِيْل) comes to Muhammadﷺ and warns him.
So Rasool Allah ﷺ stands up and leaves, without telling the Sahabah(صحابه) anything.
He just leaves, he walks away.
So, the Sahabah(صحابه) are waiting, waiting, waiting Rasool Allah doesn't show up,
they go and inquire, they go back to Madina and ask, Where is Rasool Allah ﷺ?
And he told them what happened,
that Jibreel(جبريل) came and told me that the Jews were planning to assassinate me.
Rasool Allah ﷺ sends them a letter.
He tells Muhammad Ibn Maslammah(محمد ابن مسلمه) to go to them and tell them,
اِنَّ رَسٌول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم اَرْسَلَنِيْ إلَيْكُمْ اَنْ اخْرِجُوْا من بِلَادِيْ
لَقَدْ نَقَضتُّمُ الْعهدَ الَّذِيْ جَعَلْتُ لَكُمْ
مِمَّا هَمَمْتُمْ بِه مِنَّ الْغَدْرْ
وقد أجلتكم عشراً فمن رئي بَعْدُ مِنْكُمْ ضَرَبْتُ عُنُقَهَ
This is in Tabaqaat Ibn Sa'ad(طبقات ابن سعد),
Rasool Allah ﷺ sends Muhammad Ibn Maslammah(محمد ابن مسلمه), he tell him, Go to the Jews of Bannu Nadhir(بنونضير) and tell them
I'm sent by the Messenger of Allah and he is telling you to leave from his land
because you have betrayed our agreement, by conspiring against me.
And I give you 10 days to leave, anyone seen after that will be executed.
So, you have 10 days to pack up and leave.
Otherwise, anybody who will be seen will be killed.
Now Muhammad Ibn Maslammah(محمد ابن مسلمه) was their ally in the time of Jahilliyaa(جاهليه).
They said; The last person, we would have expected to come and deliver this message to us,
would be you, Muhammad Ibn Maslammah(محمد ابن مسلمه).
Muhammad(محمد) responded back and said,
Islam has changed us and our hearts are different.
Now things are different, now we're Muslims.
Now our loyalty goes to Allahعَزّوجَلّ
and our covenant with Allahعَزّوجَلّ is more important than our former covenants with you.
And our agreement with Rasool Allah ﷺ to support him and help him and obey him
is more important than our former agreements with you.
تَغَّيَّرَتُ الْقُلُوْبْ وَمَحَى الّاِسْلَامَ الْعهُوْدْ
Our hearts are different and Islam has abrogated, the covenants
their initial reaction was to accept and leave peacefully.
But Abdullah Bin Obaeye(عبدالله بن اُبَي) the head of Nifaaq(نفاق), the head of the hypocrites, he tells them;
If you stay firm and resist, We will not give up on you,
If you fight, We will fight along with you
and if you are expelled, We will leave with you.
Pretty straightforward, we are going to stand side by side.
Do not leave, stay put and fight
and we will help you and he told them,
I have 2000 men from my people and from other Arabs who are sympathetic to our cause.
Don't leave.
So, this strengthen the Yahood(يهود) and they changed their mind and they decided to stay and fight.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: When he heard the news. He said:
حَارَبَتِ الْيَهُوْد
The Jews want to fight.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ laid siege to their territory.
By the way, let me go back to the message that was sent to them through Muhammad Ibn Maslammah(محمد ابن مسلمه).
Notice here that Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
اَنْ اخْرِجُوْ مِن بِلَادِيْ
Leave from my land.
So, now Rasool Allah ﷺ is calling Madina his land, he's not the guest anymore.
This is his land.
And this also shows you the obedience that the people of Madina gave to Rasool Allah ﷺ
so that Rasool Ullah was now ruling over them, even though he's not from Madina
and this becomes his territory and it's named after him Madina-Tu-Rasool Ullah(مدينة رسول الله),
the city of Rasool Allah ﷺ that's the meaning of Madina.
It's called Madina-Tu-Rasool Ullah(مدينة الرسول الله), the city of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
Anyway Rasool Allah ﷺ laid siege to the fortresses of Bannu Nadhir(بنونضير)
and Bannu Nadhir(بنونضير) were rich, and they had these fortresses
and then outside they had, acres and acres of agriculture land, palm groves,
which they depended on for their livelihood.
So, their plan was to remain in their fortresses,
until Muhammadﷺ and the Muslims get tired and leave them.
They have water, they have food, they have money so they can survive a long siege.
And again, their livelihood was based on these or at least part of their livelihood was based on the palm groves,
Rasool Allah ﷺ used a strategy that completely baffled Al-Yahood(اليهود)
and probably was the cause of their surrender.
Rasool Allah ﷺ started burning down their palm trees.
Now, this drove the Yahood(يهود) crazy
because you know what are we going to stay and do in Madina,
if we lose all of our farmland, why carry on the fight
our existence in Madina, depends at least partially on these farms
and if they are destroyed and we're here, we're talking about trees that take years to bear fruit.
So if Rasool Allah ﷺ burns them down.
How long will it take us to plant them again and how will we live until then?
So, this completely took them by surprise.
And they sent to Muhammadﷺ and they told him;
O Muhammad(محمد), You used to forbid, causing destruction and criticize those who did so,
why are you cutting down and burning our date palms.?
See the reason why I took the Yahood(يهود) by surprise
is that they didn't expect Muhammad(محمد) to do so.
Muhammadﷺ used to prevent people from causing unnecessary destruction of property.
And we know that in Islam, there are some commands given by Rasool Allah ﷺ, not to cut down trees.
ولا تقطعوا شجرة
And now Muhammadﷺ is doing that himself.
So, the Yahood(يهود) were surprised and they told Muhammadﷺ, what's going on.?
كُنْتَ تَنْهَى عَنْ فَسَادِ فِى الاَرضْ
You used to tell people not to do this and now you're doing it yourself.
Now, we'll come back to that later on and talk about, why Rasool Allah ﷺ did that, anyway.
So, they made an offer, they asked Muhammadﷺ to allow them to evacuate
and spare their lives, and allow them to take their wealth with them.
Rasool Allah ﷺ agreed with the following conditions.
You do not take any weapons with you, your arms you leave them behind
and you're only allowed to carry one camel load,
you're only allowed to carry one camel load,
if your property is more than that, then you leave it behind, and they agreed.
So the one responsible for the oversight of this evacuation was Muhammad Ibn Maslammah رضي الله عنه.
Every three men were given one camel for transportation
and one camel for taking their property.
Ibn Is'haaq(ابن اسحاق) said;
They, therefore loaded their belongings on their camels, to the extent that they could bear,
some of their men tore down their houses and remove the door lentils
which they mounted on the backs of their camels and took away.
Some of them had a lot of money they were hoarding treasures Salaam Ibn Abil-Haqeeq(سلام ابن ابى الحقيق), for example,
He filled the skin of a bull, he filled it with gold and silver.
And he said;
هَذَ الَّذِي أعدَدْنَاه لِرَفْعِ الْاَرْضِ وَخَفْضِهَا
وَاِنْ كُنَّا تَرَكْنَا نَخْلًا وَفِيْ خَيْبَرً نَخْلَ
This is what we have prepared for the ups and downs of this world.
And if we are leaving behind our palm groves, we'll find palm groves in Khaybar(خيبر).
No problem, we're going to leave our farms that's fine but
I'm ready to leave I've collected all of this money, throughout the years for the misfortunate times like these.
So, he had this huge load of gold and silver that he was taken away with him.
They went to Khaybar(خيبر),
some of them went to Khaybar(خيبر) and some of them went to Ash-Shaam(الشام).
And they had a lot of pride,
and Bannu Nadhir(بنونضير), were very respected among the Jewish tribes of the area,
they were considered to be the learned ones and the scholars among them.
And they didn't want the Muslims to laugh at their fortune,
and they wanted to show that what happened is something that, we are not upset with
and that they didn't lose anything and they were trying to put on that face.
So, when they went to Khaybar(خيبر), Abdullah Bin Abi Bakr(عبدالله بن ابي بكر) said;
they were received by women and young men and gifts with tambourines, flutes
and girls walking behind them, singing boldly and with pride,
nothing similar is related of any tribe of people in their era.
So, even though these were people who were defeated and driven out of their land,
they were welcomed at Khaybar(خيبر) as heroes.
And that's because they didn't want the Muslims to feel sorry for them or to laugh at their misfortune.
When in reality it was a huge setback for them, giving up their houses and their lands.
Allahعَزّوجَلّ says in Qur'an,
يُخْرِبُونَ بُيُوتَهُمْ بِأَيْدِيهِمْ
They were tearing down their houses, with their own hands and
if you build your house and you lived in your house for years and you have all of these memories attached to this house.
And then you're tearing it down with your own hand, how painful is that.?
Some lessons from Ghazawat Bannu Nadhir(غزوة بنونضير),
the entire Surah(سورة) was revealed talking about this Ghazwah(غزوة) it is Surah Tul Hashr(سورة الحشر)
and Ibn Abbas(ابن عباس) used to call it, the Surah(سورة) of Bannu Nadhir(بنونضير).
We'll go through some of the Ayaat(آيات) of this Surah(سورة) Allahعَزّوجَلّ says;
هُوَ الَّذِي أَخْرَجَ الَّذِينَ كَفَرُوا مِنْ أَهْلِ الْكِتَابِ مِنْ دِيَارِهِمْ لِأَوَّلِ الْحَشْرِ
مَا ظَنَنْتُمْ أَنْ يَخْرُجُوا
وَظَنُّوا أَنَّهُمْ مَانِعَتُهُمْ حُصُونُهُمْ مِنَ اللَّهِ
فَأَتَاهُمُ اللَّهُ مِنْ حَيْثُ لَمْ يَحْتَسِبُوا
وَقَذَفَ فِي قُلُوبِهِمُ الرُّعْبَ
يُخْرِبُونَ بُيُوتَهُمْ بِأَيْدِيهِمْ وَأَيْدِي الْمُؤْمِنِينَ فَاعْتَبِرُوا يَا أُولِي الْأَبْصَارِ۝
It is He, Who expelled the ones, who disbelieved
among the People of the Scripture from their homes, at the first gathering.
You did not think they would leave
and they thought that there that their fortresses would protect them from Allah,
so here Allah is saying that the expectations before on your side and on their side is that you can't drive them out.
So, their fortresses were strong and powerful and they had plenty of fighters.
They had a lot of wealth to finance war.
So the expectation, Allahعَزّوجَلّ is saying that your expectation and their expectation was that they wouldn't leave.
So, the way it looked from the out start
is that it will not be possible to drive them out nevertheless they did.
Why? Allah did so.
هُوَ الَّذِي أَخْرَجَ
He's the One, He is the One, Who expelled them.
Allah says it is He, Who expelled the ones, who disbelieved
among the People of the Scripture from their homes at the first gathering.
You did not think they would leave, and they thought that their fortresses would protect them from Allah.
And over here, Allah is talking about fortresses but this could apply to anything.
I mean any nation or any superpower who thinks that their weapons,
no matter what these weapons are can stand between them and the Qadar(قدر) of Allah are mistaken.
Whether these weapons are nuclear bombs or aircraft carriers or powerful airplanes or
bombs, whatever, huge army million of fighters.
If Allahعَزّوجَلّ wants to defeat a nation, that nation will be defeated.
No one can stand between Allahعَزّوجَلّ and giving victory to His servants.
Then Allah says but the decree of Allah came upon them from where they had not expected.
See, no matter how strong your army is
no matter how well your preparations are, how good your training is,
no matter how many types of weapons you have.
There are always going to be some gaps,
there are always going to be some points of weakness
and Allahعَزّوجَلّ knows these.
And Allahعَزّوجَلّ will attack the enemies of Allah, through these points of weakness.
Now how did it happen with the people of Bannu Nadhir(بنونضير)?
Allahعَزّوجَلّ said;
But the decree of Allah, came upon them, from where they had not expected
and He cast terror into their hearts.
This was the soldier of Allah عَزّوجَلّ that defeated Bannu Nadhir(بنونضير).
Fear.
They were horrified,
Allahعَزّوجَلّ cast fear into their hearts.
So, if the heart is terrified, it doesn't make a difference,
what arms you have, or how well fortified you are.
And that's why Ibn Qayyim(ابن قيم) says
that the Romans and Persians had stronger bodies greater numbers and more arms than the Muslims had,
but their hearts failed them when they needed the most.
When the Sahabah رضي الله عنهم stood in battle, in front of the Romans and Persians,
in terms of physical ability, they probably were not as strong as their opponents,
their training was definitely less, their numbers were definitely less
and the arms assortment that the Sahabah(صحابه) had, was very limited compared to what their opponents had.
However the Sahabah(صحابه) had Eeman(إيمان) and that Eeman(إيمان) made their heart steadfast,
while the enemies of Allahعَزّوجَلّ were attached to Duniya(دنيا)
and Allahعَزّوجَلّ cast fear in their hearts and they lost.
So, Allahعَزّوجَلّ says, So take warning, or people of vision.
And then Allah says;
وَلَوْلَا أَنْ كَتَبَ اللَّهُ عَلَيْهِمُ الْجَلَاءَ لَعَذَّبَهُمْ فِي الدُّنْيَا ۖ
وَلَهُمْ فِي الْآخِرَةِ عَذَابُ النَّارِ۝
And if not, that Allah had the decreed for them evacuation
He would have punished them, in this world
and for them in the Hereafter is the punishment of fire.
So, Allah is saying if, the people of Nadhir(نضير) didn't evacuate
their punishment would have been execution, which is even worse.
That would be the punishment in Duniyah(دُنِيَّا)
and the punishment in the hereafter, would be even greater.
ذَٰلِكَ بِأَنَّهُمْ شَاقُّوا اللَّهَ وَرَسُولَهُ
وَمَنْ يُشَاقِّ اللَّهَ فَإِنَّ اللَّهَ شَدِيدُ الْعِقَابِ۝
That is because, they oppose Allah and His messenger
and whoever opposes Allah then indeed, Allah is severe in penalty.
So, this act Allahعَزّوجَلّ of defeating Bannu Nadhir(بنونضير)
is because of their disbelief in Allah and His messengers.
So, Allahعَزّوجَلّ is just,
Allahعَزّوجَلّ did not punish them without deserving that punishment.
Allahعَزّوجَلّ punish them because of standing against Islam.
So, anyone who stands against Islam either an individual or a nation
is calling upon themselves the Wrath of Allahعَزّوجَلّ.
Allah says;
مَا قَطَعْتُمْ مِنْ لِينَةٍ أَوْ تَرَكْتُمُوهَا قَائِمَةً عَلَىٰ أُصُولِهَا فَبِإِذْنِ اللَّهِ وَلِيُخْزِيَ الْفَاسِقِينَ۝
Whatever you have cut down of their palm trees,
or left standing on their trunks, it was by the permission of Allah,
and so He would disgrace the defiantly disobedient,
so we go back to this issue of Muhammadﷺ, telling people not to destroy property and then he did it himself.
First of all, this was done by the permission of Allah, according to this Ayah(آية)
فَبِإِذْنِ اللَّهِ
It was by the permission of Allah.
The ones that you cut down and the ones that remain that was by the permission of Allah.
Why?
وَلِيُخْزِيَ الْفَاسِقِينَ
He would disgrace, the defiantly disobedient.
Rasool Allah ﷺ has given instructions that trees should not be cut down
women, children and old men should not be killed.
He also said that monks, who are monasteries should not be killed.
However, we find that with every one of these rules,
there are incidents that go against the rule.
So, here in Ghazwat(غزوة) Bannu Nadhir(بنونضير),
Rasool Allah ﷺ has given orders to burn the palms down.
So that is against the ruling of cutting down trees.
And then there's what is called Bayaat(بيآت)
and this is attacking at night, you attack the dwellings of people at night
and the residents are killed.
And Salmah Bin Aqwah(سلمة بن الاكوع) said;
I myself participated in Bayaat(بيآت),
and I killed the residents of nine houses with my own hand.
And this is in Sahih Muslim(صحيح مسلم).
Now obviously here, you have men, women, children killed
because it's at night and they can be distinguished.
So, this goes against the ruling of not killing women, children and old men.
And then we also know that Rasool Allah ﷺ has ordered the execution of two women
and one of those woman was, the woman who tried to poison Rasool Allah ﷺ a Yahoodi(يهودي) woman,
she was executed by Rasool Allah ﷺ.
And we know that there were incidences where old men were killed.
So, this goes against that ruling.
And with the killing of monks, we know Salah-Ud-Din(صلاح الدين) for example
would specifically even though, he was very tolerant with the Crusaders
he would not let the members of the military religious orders
such as the Templers or the hospitalors, he wouldn't let them go free, he would kill them.
They were all executed, if they would land in his hands.
And these were monks, these were religious men.
So, this goes against the instruction of not killing monks.
So what's going on here?
How can we have this contradiction?
The answer to that is the following.
Islam is a tolerant religion.
And the religion of Islam has laid down rules for engagement.
There are rules that govern Jihad(جهاد) Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله).
And these rules are to protect the rights of others and to protect the innocent life.
However, whenever the enemy tries to take advantage of these rules
and harm the Muslims these rules are suspended.
So, if the enemy tries to take advantage of Muslims
by using these restrictions against them.
Then the Muslims are allowed to put those rules aside.
To sum it up,
Islam will not allow its tolerance to be used against it.
So in this situation here Rasool Allah ﷺ ordered the cutting down of the trees of Bannu Nadhir(بنونضير),
because Bannu Nadhir(بنونضير) were planning on a long siege.
And they were depending on their palm trees
while they deserved the punishment because of their betrayal,
and because of their plotting to assassinate Rasool Allah ﷺ.
So Rasool Allah ﷺ did not allow them to use his rules against the Muslims,
and therefore he ordered the cutting down of trees.
Allah عَزّوجَلّ says;
وَمَا أَفَاءَ اللَّهُ عَلَىٰ رَسُولِهِ مِنْهُمْ فَمَا أَوْجَفْتُمْ
فَمَا أَوْجَفْتُمْ عَلَيْهِ مِنْ خَيْلٍ وَلَا رِكَابٍ وَلَٰكِنَّ اللَّهَ يُسَلِّطُ رُسُلَهُ
وَلَٰكِنَّ اللَّهَ يُسَلِّطُ رُسُلَهُ عَلَىٰ مَنْ يَشَاءُ
وَاللَّهُ عَلَىٰ كُلِّ شَيْءٍ قَدِيرٌ۝
مَا أَفَاءَ اللَّهُ عَلَىٰ رَسُولِهِ مِنْ أَهْلِ الْقُرَىٰ فَلِلَّهِ وَلِلرَّسُولِ وَلِذِي الْقُرْبَىٰ
وَلِذِي الْقُرْبَىٰ وَالْيَتَامَىٰ وَالْمَسَاكِينِ وَابْنِ السَّبِيلِ كَيْ لَا يَكُونَ دُولَةً بَيْنَ الْأَغْنِيَاءِ مِنْكُمْ
وَمَا آتَاكُمُ الرَّسُولُ فَخُذُوهُ وَمَا نَهَاكُمْ عَنْهُ فَانْتَهُوا
وَاتَّقُوا اللَّهَ إِنَّ اللَّهَ شَدِيدُ الْعِقَابِ۝
And what Allah restored of property to His messenger, from them
you did not spare for it, in an expedition, any horses or camels.
But Allah gives His messengers power over whom He wills
and Allah is over all things competent.
And what Allah restored to His messenger from the people of the towns
it is for Allah and for the messenger and for his nearer relatives
and the orphans and the stranded traveler,
so that it will not be a perpetual distribution among the rich from among you
and whatever the messenger has given you take
and what he has forbidden you, refrain from
and fear Allah indeed Allah is severe in penalty.
So, this is talking about the rulings of Fae(فيئ).
What is Fae(فيئ)?
Ghaneemah(غنيمه) is the name given to spoils of war
that are taken by the army after a fight.
Fae(فيئ) are spoils of war that are taken by the army without a fight.
Since no fighting occurred with Bannu Nadhir(بنونضير),
since they surrendered and accepted to evacuate and leave behind their property
except for what they can carry, since no fighting occurred.
The ruling of what they leave behind is that it goes to Rasool Allah ﷺ.
So the ruling of Ghaneemah(غنيمة), which is to split it into five portions
four of those portions go to the fighters, does not apply here
the entire thing goes to Rasool Allah ﷺ
and he has authority to distribute it as he sees appropriate.
So, these Ayaat(آيات) are talking about the ruling of Fae(فيئ).
This was a new source of income for the Muslims
and Ibn Is'haaq(اِبن إسحاق) says, they left their properties for the Messenger of Allah.
These consisted of their palm trees and their farms,
these became his personal property to dispose of, as he wished.
So, it was up to Rasool Allah ﷺ.
Rasool Ullah calls the Ansaar(أنصار), Al-Aos(الأوس) and Al-Khazraj(الخزرج), and he tells them.
If you want I can split this money among you all,
and the Muhajireen(مهاجرين) continue living in your houses and working in your farms,
or if you want I can distribute this money among the Muhajireen(مهاجرين) only.
And they would leave your houses and not take any share from your harvest.
Because if you go back earlier, we talked about that the Ansaar(أنصار) offered
that they would share the harvest of their land with the Muhajireen(مهاجرين),
something they offered they didn't have to,
but they were willing to share their harvest with the Muhajiroon(مهاجرون).
So now Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
it's up to you, I could distribute this among you all
and the Muhajireen(مهاجرين) continue living in your houses,
or they can move out and I'll give them this money of Bannu Nadhir(بنونضير),
so the Ansaar(أنصار) agreed and they said that
you could distribute it to our brothers from Muhajiroon(مهاجرون),
and if you want us to carry on giving them a share of our farms,
we don't have a problem with that either.
And this shows you the generosity of Al-Ansaar رضي الله عنهم.
So, now Al-Muhajiroon(مهاجرون) moved into the houses of Bannu Nadhir(بنونضير).
So the difficult financial situation of Al-Muhajiroon(مهاجرون) was now lifted
and their financial situation was improving.
Now they have the houses of Bannu Nadhir(بنونضير)
and they also have the farms of Bannu Nadhir(بنونضير),
which were split among the Muhajiroon(مهاجرون) only
and only two men from Al-Ansaar(أنصار) were given a share
and these two men were Sahal Bin Haneef(سهل بن حنيف) and Abu-Dujana(ابودجانه)
because they complained of their poverty so, Rasool Allah ﷺ gave them some.
Ibn Kathir(ابن كثير) says, these were specifically for the Messenger of Allah
he would set aside his family's expenses for a year
and then whatever riding beast or weapons remained
he would treat as military supplies to be used in the cause of Allah the Almighty and Glorious.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ now also, finally he had some wealth.
Before that he would live on gifts that he would get from the Sahabah رضي الله عنهم.
Let's talk here about the livelihood of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
We know that he started out his life as a shepherd.
That was his first profession,
number two, after that he worked as a businessman
and he got to Khadeejah(خديجه) and he became her business manager,
he would take care her business, for her.
But when he was given the Risala(رسالة), Prophethood he stopped working.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ discontinued working as either a shepherd, or in business.
Rasool Allah ﷺ devoted his entire time for Da'wah(دعوة).
So, he would live off the money of Khadeejah رضي الله عنها and from his uncle, Abu Talib(ابو طالب),
and then when he moved to Madina, the Ansaar(أنصار) would help Rasool Allah ﷺ,
obviously he's the Messenger of Allah, so he cannot accept Sadaqah(صدقه)
but they would give him gifts.
Now since this money of Fae(فيئ), all of it goes back to him
he would take from it, his expenses for a year
and then the rest he would spend in Jihad(جهاد) Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله).
Rasool Allah ﷺ says;
جُعِلَ رِزْقِيْ تَحْتَ ظِلْ رُمْحِيْ
My provisions come from beneath my spear.
So, my provisions come from fighting in the cause of Allahعَزّوجَلّ,
that was the source of income for Rasool Allah ﷺ
and he wasn't an employee, he didn't run a business
all of his income would come from Jihad(جهاد) Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله), from the spoils of war.
جُعِلَ رِزْقِيْ تَحْتَ ظِلْ رُمْحِيْ
My provisions come from under my spear.
Anas Ibn Malik رضي الله عنه said;
A man might donate to him, his palms or whatever else Allah might wish
up to when Quraidha(قريظة) and Nadhir(نضير) were conquered for him
there after he began giving it back.
So, now finally Rasool Allah ﷺ has money to give back.
Before that, he was taking now he's giving.
Surat(سورة) Bannu Nadhir(بنونضير) also talks about the Munafiqoon(منافقون).
These Munafiqeen(منافقين), who sent to Bannu Nadhir(بنونضير) and told them
if you stay firm and resist, we will not give up on you,
if you fight we'll fight along with you and if you're expelled, we will leave with you.
Allahعَزّوجَلّ said about them;
أَلَمْ تَرَ إِلَى الَّذِينَ نَافَقُوا يَقُولُونَ لِإِخْوَانِهِمُ الَّذِينَ كَفَرُوا مِنْ أَهْلِ الْكِتَابِ
لَئِنْ أُخْرِجْتُمْ لَنَخْرُجَنَّ مَعَكُمْ وَلَا نُطِيعُ فِيكُمْ أَحَدًا أَبَدًا
وَإِنْ قُوتِلْتُمْ لَنَنْصُرَنَّكُمْ وَاللَّهُ يَشْهَدُ إِنَّهُمْ لَكَاذِبُونَ۝
لَئِنْ أُخْرِجُوا لَا يَخْرُجُونَ مَعَهُمْ وَلَئِنْ قُوتِلُوا لَا يَنْصُرُونَهُمْ وَلَئِنْ نَصَرُوهُمْ لَيُوَلُّنَّ الْأَدْبَارَ
وَلَئِنْ نَصَرُوهُمْ لَيُوَلُّنَّ الْأَدْبَارَ ثُمَّ لَا يُنْصَرُونَ۝
Have you not considered, those who practice hypocrisy
saying to their brothers, meaning the Jews,
who have disbelieved among the People of the Scripture.
If you are expelled, we will surely leave with you
and we will not obey in regard to you anyone, ever.
And if you are fought we will surely aid you, but Allah testifies that they are liars.
If they are expelled, they will not leave with them.
And if they are fought, they will not aid them.
And even if they should aid them they will surely turn their backs, then thereafter they will not be aided.
These Munafiqoon(منافقون) are just talk, but they're empty they're worthless.
They promised the Jews that they will stand with them
if they are fought against, they will fight with them,
if they're expelled, they're going to leave with them.
None of this happened it was all lies.
And Allah عَزّوجَلّ is revealing to us here some of the characteristics of Munafiqoon(منافقون).
Therefore we shouldn't be afraid of Al-Munafiqoon(منافقون).
There are Munafiqoon(منافقون) in the Ummah(أمة), they're very loud.
They talk a lot and they threatened a lot, but all of it is empty talk.
So the Muslims should not be threatened by these type of people
and they deceived Al-Yahood(اليهود).
The Yahood(اليهود) were waiting for help to come from Abdullah Bin Obaeye(عبدالله بن اُبَيئ)
and none of it, showed up.
Allahعَزّوجَلّ says even, if they help them they would have lost
it wouldn't have made a difference anyway.
Allahعَزّوجَلّ then says,
لَأَنْتُمْ أَشَدُّ رَهْبَةً فِي صُدُورِهِمْ مِنَ اللَّهِ
ذَٰلِكَ بِأَنَّهُمْ قَوْمٌ لَا يَفْقَهُونَ۝
لَا يُقَاتِلُونَكُمْ جَمِيعًا إِلَّا فِي قُرًى مُحَصَّنَةٍ أَوْ مِنْ وَرَاءِ جُدُرٍ
بَأْسُهُمْ بَيْنَهُمْ شَدِيدٌ
تَحْسَبُهُمْ جَمِيعًا وَقُلُوبُهُمْ شَتَّىٰ
ذَٰلِكَ بِأَنَّهُمْ قَوْمٌ لَا يَعْقِلُونَ۝
You believers are more fearful within their hearts from Allah,
they fear you more then they fear Allah,
you believers, and this is talking about all of Al-Kuffar(الكفار), not only Munafiqeen(منافقين),
Al-Munafiqeen(منافقين), Al-Yahood(اليهود) all of the Kuffar(كفار).
You believers are more fearful within their breasts, than Allah.
This is because they are people, who do not understand.
They will not fight you all, except within fortified cities or from behind walls
and here Allahعَزّوجَلّ is disclosing to us this quality of Al-Kuffar(الكفار).
They are not going to fight Muslims unless they are well fortified.
Subhan Allah(سبحان الله) this fear of Al-Kuffar(الكفار) translates itself in two different forms.
In the time of Rasool Allah ﷺ it was these fortresses
in the time of crusades, it manifested itself in architectural wonders,
in the land of Ash-sham(الشام),
the most beautiful works of architecture are the castles of the Crusaders.
Yes it is wonderful work of architecture,
but it's also reflects the fear that they had from the soldiers of Allahعَزّوجَلّ.
Salah-Ud-Din(صلاح الدين) wasn't building all of these castles, these castles were built by the Crusaders.
And today the enemies of Allahعَزّوجَلّ will not fight the Muslims
except if they're well fortified.
Look at this wall, that is now built in Falastine(فلسطين).
That's a reflection of the fear.
Subhaan Allah(سبحان الله) that wall is a fulfillment of this Ayah(آية) of Qur'an.
They will not fight except from behind the wall
or from a well protected cockpit in a plane
or from the bowels of a ship
but they do not have a courage to come out and fight like the the children of Al-Intifaadha(الانتفاضة)
out there in the open, fighting for Allahعَزّوجَلّ.
Allahعَزّوجَلّ says: Their violence among themselves is severe.
This is to tell the Muslims that even though they gang up against you
they come together and fight you.
But their hearts are different, and they have hatred among themselves.
Look at what the kuffar(كفار) do to each other.
In World War One, you have 10 million killed in World War Two 50 million.
Look at the wars that happened, among the European nations
look at the wars in Africa look at wars in all over the world.
So, don't think that the kuffar(كفار) are all one.
No, they have differences among themselves
but when it comes to Islam, Yes, they unify and they come and fight together,
but we should realize that they have differences among themselves too.
وَقُلُوبُهُمْ شَتَّىٰ
Their violence among themselves is severe.
Again World War One and World War Two are an example of that.
You think they are together but their hearts are diverse.
That is because they are people who do not reason.
لَأَنْتُمْ أَشَدُّ رَهْبَةً فِي صُدُورِهِمْ مِنَ اللَّهِ
ذَٰلِكَ بِأَنَّهُمْ قَوْمٌ لَا يَفْقَهُونَ۝
لَا يُقَاتِلُونَكُمْ جَمِيعًا إِلَّا فِي قُرًى مُحَصَّنَةٍ أَوْ مِنْ وَرَاءِ جُدُرٍ ۚ
بَأْسُهُمْ بَيْنَهُمْ شَدِيدٌ
تَحْسَبُهُمْ جَمِيعًا وَقُلُوبُهُمْ شَتَّىٰ
ذَٰلِكَ بِأَنَّهُمْ قَوْمٌ لَا يَعْقِلُونَ۝
There is like the example of those, shortly before them,
they tasted the bad consequences of their affair
and they will have a painful punishment.
This is talking about Bannu Qainuqah(بنوقينقاع)
who were driven out of Madina before Bannu Nadhir(بنونضير),
Bannu Nadhir(بنونضير) should have taken heed of what happened to Bannu Qainuqah(بنوقينقاع).
These are some lessons from the Ayaat(آيات) of Surat(سورة) An-Nadhir(النضير).
We have read the Aayat(آيات), up until about verse 16 or 15 if you want to go back and check them.
The Arabs of Madina, in the time of Jahiliyyah(جاهليه)
They had the superstition that if they have children and they keep on dying.
So the mother will have a child and then the child will die,
she will have the second child and that child will die,
they had the superstition that if you make a vow that your next child will be a Jew,
then the child will live,
this was some superstition that existed among the people of Madina, before Islam.
Because of this, they had children, who were growing up with Al-Yahood(اليهود)
as a fulfillment of those vows.
So now, when the Jews of Bannu Nadhir(بنونضير) are going to be driven out,
they came to Rasool Allah ﷺ and said;
We have some of our sons and some of our brothers are with them.
What should we do?
Rasool Allah ﷺ did not answer back, until an Ayah(آية) in Qur'an was revealed,
And that Ayah(آية) was:
لَا إِكْرَاهَ فِي الدِّينِ ۖ قَدْ تَبَيَّنَ الرُّشْدُ مِنَ الْغَيِّ ۚ
There is no compulsion in religion
and you all know this verse, it's in Surat-Ul-Baqarah(سورة البقرة) there is no compulsion in religion.
Path of good is clear on the path of evil is clear.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ told them,
This is a Sahih(صحيح) narration
قَدْ خُيِّرَ أَصْحَابكُمْ , فَإِنْ اخْتَارُوكُمْ فَهُمْ مِنْكُمْ , وَإِنْ اخْتَارُوهُمْ فَهُمْ مِنْهُمْ
Give these brothers and Sons of yours the choice,
if they choose you, then they stay with you, if they choose to be with the Jews, then they leave with them.
In other words, you cannot compel them, you cannot force them
to stay behind and become Muslim,
even though they are ethnically Arabs even though they are your own children.
These issues are not about ethnicity
and we talked about this issue of nationalism, and all of that.
Islam doesn't recognize this, it is what is in your heart that's what counts.
Islam is not against a particular race,
whether that race is the Jewish race or the white race or any race.
Islam is not against any particular race Islam is a religion for everyone.
And Rasool Allah ﷺ says;
Allahعَزّوجَلّ does not look at your forms or the color of your skin.
Allahعَزّوجَلّ looks at your hearts.
So, these children of yours even though they are part of your families,
if they choose you, then they are Muslim
if they choose the Yahood(يهود), then they have to leave with them,
and you cannot force them otherwise to become Muslim.
And this is the reason for the revelation of this Ayah(آية) that we all know in Surat-Ul-Baqarah(سورة البقرة),
لَا إِكْرَاهَ فِي الدِّينِ ۖ
Also alcohol was banned, during the siege of Bannu Nadhir(بنونضير),
that's when the Ayah(آية) prohibiting alcohol was revealed,
and you know that the prohibition of alcohol occurred in four stages, this was the final stage.
So, it's pretty late and we were talking about the fourth year of Hijrah(هجرى).
So, Muslims, continue drinking for 17 years.
It wasn't until the last six years of the life of Rasool Allah ﷺ that alcohol was banned.
وَصَلَّى الله عَلى سَيَّدِنَا محمد وَعَلى اَلِهِ وَ صَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ تَسْلِيْمًا كَثِيْرًا